Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Happy שושן פורים. Shushan Purim. We
pick up with דף מ"ו. Daf Mem Vav. We pick up at
the bottom of מ"ה עמוד ב' Mem Hey Amud Bet and we're
doing with this debate about if you worship the mountains, somebody worships
the mountains, they don't become אסור בהנאה, Asur Behana'ah, they don't become
forbidden in benefit, but the things on them do. And the question
is about the trees and so on. So the חכמים Chachamim say
that if you worship the trees there's not a problem, but רבי
יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, who was it? רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yosi bar Rebbi Yehuda and another and the רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi
Yosi Haglili says that, or the גמרא Gemara reads them to say,
is that the trees can become a problem, at least the part
that grows afterwards because of תפיסת יד אדם, Tfisat Yad Adam, because
it's something under human control. And one of the issues that we
discussed that came up in passing that Michael raised yesterday and then
afterwards I saw it was exactly explicitly discussed both in רש"י Rashi
and תוספות, Tosfos, so a little bit on this coming דף Daf
but a little bit from previous דף, Daf, so I'm sorry I
missed that, is the question about where do you draw the line
of תפיסת יד אדם? Tfisat Yad Adam? Let's say something just grew
naturally. Let's say you planted a seed; you didn't actually plant a
tree. So that actually is discussed in רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos.
רש"י Rashi assumes that if you planted a seed that still is
תפיסת יד אדם Tfisat Yad Adam and for therefore רבי יוסי, Rebbi
Yosi, if you worship what grows afterwards, it becomes forbidden, whereas not
according to the חכמים. Chachamim. And תוספות Tosfos disagrees; תוספות Tosfos says
that only if you planted it as an actual like sapling, but
if you planted it as a seed you're never really relating to
it as a tree, then even רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi would say
it's not a problem what grows afterwards. Both רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosfos agree that if it grew by itself it would not be
a problem. So according to everybody there's a certain type of a
tree that's considered just part of the landscape and your worshipping of
it can't control it and define it. And the debate is that
when you have a certain degree of control over it, you plant
it as a sapling, let's say that clearly would be the case
in the גמרא, Gemara, seed is debate, but if you plant it
as a sapling, there רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi and רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rebbi Yosi Haglili and רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi bar
Rebbi Yehuda say that you have enough control over it you can
define at least what grows afterwards and the חכמים Chachamim say you
cannot.
So meaning if it grew on its own then even if you
worshipped it when it was this little sprout and then it grew
to this big tree it would still be okay.
Correct. Anything that grew on its own is not a problem. Now
okay, and but part of the way they learn it from is
the double language in the פסוקים Psukim or the way the גמרא
Gemara attributes it to. One verse speaks about chopping down the אשרה
Asherah and the other verse speaks about destroying it completely, burning it.
So the point is you chop it down and you can retain
the base if it is something that you worshipped after it grew.
But something that you worshipped that was planted for the sake of
being a tree of worship, that you have to totally destroy. And
by the way I should say that's the חכמים's Chachamim case also
of when you would have to destroy a tree. If you worshipped
it after it was growing, no problem, but what's the case of
the אשרה Asherah in the תורה? Torah? When it was planted for
that purpose. So planted for that purpose you totally destroy it. According
to רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi bar Rebbi Yehuda the
cutting it down but leaving the stump is when you worshipped it
after it was already growing. For the חכמים Chachamim who would not
say you have to destroy it at all in that case, the
point of the two stages of cutting it down and then burning
it is two stages of destruction. You come into the land you
destroy everything that's very visible and that's out there and so on,
then you conquer the land and then you go back and you
fully destroy it.
He's not getting any benefit, whoever it is that worshipped it, right?
Can't get any benefit from it even though somebody else could.
One more time, if you worshipped it?
The person who worships it, it would be אסור בהנאה Asur Behana'ah
to him or her?
No, it's אסור בהנאה Asur Behana'ah for everybody.
If you worship a tree?
Well, if it's a tree that doesn't have תפיסת יד אדם Tfisat
Yad Adam it's not forbidden to anybody. And if it's a tree
that does have תפיסת יד אדם Tfisat Yad Adam according to רבי
יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi bar Rebbi Yehuda or was planted
for that sake, it's forbidden to everyone. You do not have a
case of it's only forbidden for you. It's not a קנס. K'nas.
It's a reality that something that was worshipped as עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah now becomes an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and is forbidden for
everyone. Okay, so now we pick up, let's repeat,
let's pick up at the bottom of מ"ה עמוד ב', Mem Hey
Amud Bet, we'll review that a little bit. The גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רב הונא רדוף אחר
כך שרוף.
Amar Rav Huna:
Radof achar kach srof.
So according to the חכמים Chachamim the two stages of cutting down
and then burning it is you cut it down, you then conquer
the nation, you conquer the land, and then you go back and
you destroy it.
רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה האי סברא מנא ליה Rebbi Yosi bar
Rebbi Yehuda: Hai sevara minalei? Where does he get this idea of
two stages? נפקא ליה מאבד תאבדון, Nafka lei mi'abbed te'abbedun,
surely destroy. It's a double language. אבד: Abbed: first destroy one go
through, ואחר כך תאבדון: ve'achar kach te'abbedun: then go back and destroy
it again. ורבנן האי מבעי ליה Verabbanan: Hai miba'ei lei? What do
they do with the double language? לעוקר עבודת כוכבים שצריך לשרש אחריה.
Le'oker avodat kochavim shetzarich lesharesh achareiha.
It's not enough that you uproot it, you have to dig up,
dig up its roots, you have to dig in and get its
deep roots as well. So when you are going to destroy it
you have to make sure you fully destroy it,
and obviously that's also metaphorically significant as well. It's not enough to
destroy a bad phenomenon; you have to go dig, dig deep into
to get out its roots so it doesn't sprout out again. רבי
יוסי בר רבי יהודה לשרש אחריה מנא ליה Rebbi Yosi bar Rebbi
Yehuda: Lesharesh achareiha minalei? Where does he know that from? נפקא ליה
מואבדתם שמם מן המקום ההוא, Nafka lei mive'ibadtem shemam min hamakom hahu,
completely to wipe out their name means to make sure that it
never resurfaces. Okay.
Psychologically also.
What? Psychologically, if you don't get to the base of what the
problem is.
Right, that's exactly, that's a good point. If you just deal with
the what's it called its manifestations, its symptoms, and not the root
cause, there you go, that's the word root, it'll just come up
again. Good point. Yep. Okay.
ורבנן ההוא לכנות לשם. v'rabbanan hahu l'chanos l'shem. This idea of wiping
out their name is to give it a replacement name. It's more
literal, to actually not mention its name again. At this time you're
talking about a ברייתא. braita. רבי אלעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. מנין
לעוקר עבודה זרה שצריך לשרש אחריה. minayin l'oker avodah zarah she-tzarich l'sharesh
achareha. How do you know if you uproot it, that you pull
it out of the ground, you have to dig deep after its
root? תלמוד לומר ואבדתם את שמם. talmud lomar v'ibadetem et shemam. You
destroy their name. Top of מ"ו עמוד א'. Mem Vav Amud Aleph.
אמר לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva said to
him, והלא כבר נאמר אבד תאבדון, v'halo kvar ne'emar abed t'abedun, surely
destroy it. So we already know there the idea of לשרש אחריה.
l'sharesh achareha. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר ואבדתם את שמם? im ken
mah talmud lomar v'ibadetem et shemam? What's the extra idea of destroying
the name? מן המקום ההוא, min hamakom hahu, לכנות לשם, l'chanos l'shem,
to give it a substitute name. יכול לשבח, yachol l'shevach, maybe the
substitute name should be a praiseworthy name. Someone says, what? לשבח סלקא
דעתך? l'shevach salka dach-tach? Why, what type of crazy question is that?
אלא יכול לא לשבח ולא לגנאי, ela yachol lo l'shevach v'lo l'gnai,
maybe it just means a substitute name but not necessarily a one
that is a negative name, but just to replace the name. So
if you had a place that was called, I don't know, Thursday,
which is Thor's day, we should call it something else. We should
call it, you know, יום חמישי Yom Chamishi or something, but you
know, it doesn't mean that you have to come up with a
שם גנאי, shem gnai, okay?
So you just do something so that you're not constantly still using
that name. You don't say you're going to, what's a good name
of a locale? I mean all the saint places, you know, St.
Louis, St. whatever. Every saint place.
Do we not supposed to be saying that?
Well, that's about Christianity in general. Anyway, anyway, this also particularly in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Is that really the case that this only applies in Eretz Yisrael?
I don't know, I mean it was a general Jewish attitude I'm
going to talk about it. אלא יכול לא לשבח ולא לגנאי, ela
yachol lo l'shevach v'lo l'gnai, תלמוד לומר שקץ תשקצנו, talmud lomar shakeitz
t'shaktzenu, surely abominate it. ותעב תתעבנו, v'ta'ev t'ta'avenu, כי חרם הוא, ki
cherem hu, and you know and it should be repulsive because it
is under the ban. So that means that part of this removing
the name comes with a sense of disgust and treating it as
a repulsive. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So how do you do this?
היו קורין אותה בית גליא, hayu korin otah Beit Galya,
if it was called Beit Galya, which is the house of, like
Rashi says, I don't know if this is correct, but Rashi says
it means like waves, like a high place, a high house. So
קורין אותה בית כריא, korin otah Beit Karya, you talk, you call
it the place of a ditch, okay? So it's a slight play
on the words, but it makes it very negative. עין כל, Ein
Kol, the eye that sees all, okay, so instead you call it
עין קוץ, Ein Kotz, the eye with a thorn in it. Okay,
so it sounds similar but it's just a slight difference. So this,
by the way, was a very,
this is very, you know, there's a good Jewish, I don't know
good, but whatever, there's a strong, long Jewish tradition about this, about
referring to things of other religions, you know, in derogatory language. Sometimes
it's very creative, like I told you, they call a house of
worship, instead of בית תפילה, Beit Tefillah, I can't even say it
right, right, instead of a בית תפילה, Beit Tefillah, a house of
prayer, they call it בית תפלה, Beit Tiflah, a house of nonsense.
There's some other good ones. I'm trying to remember them. Anyway, so
they have some like standard ways in which they refer to them
and they use this very negative. Now, first of all, just as
a curiosity, there's actually an English word for this process as opposed
to euphemism, which is like which is calling something something positive instead
of something negative, it's dysphemism, which is calling something negative instead of
something positive. Anyway, so, or another version of the cacophemism, but I
think that's more about melodic than about anyway the connotations.
You know, and to some degree you understand this, right? You're like
a minority religion and you know, there's this dominant culture, dominant religion,
that is trying to, on a good day, tolerate you, and on
a bad day, oppress and kill you and murder and you know,
whatever, and, so, and you're constantly getting all of these negative messages
about how you're terrible and so on, and you need some type,
sometimes, you know, what do they say like people, negative emotions are
more easily accessible than positive ones or whatever. You know, so you
need something to sort of give people a certain sense of feeling
good, or feeling like in the end we're right, that's all
nonsense, ways of sort of being able
to to strengthen their sense of their own beliefs and, and sometimes
it comes at the expense of the other, especially again when you're
the minority, the oppressed minority. So it's like you can certainly totally
understand it. It's a bit of a problem now when those attitudes
are sustained in certain types of more
like חרדי Charedi or חסידיש Chasidish culture because that's sort of they're
still living, A, because they're not as open to modern ideas and
they're still living in a more segregated community and they're sort of
a little bit more still living in the past, but it constantly
reinforces this way of looking at the other, constantly like devaluing others'
religions, others' forms of worship, "Oh, that's nonsense, what you're doing," the
נארשקייט, nareshkeit, the this and the that, "Mine is the only religion
that's true, that matters," and so on. So
it's anyway, so there's obviously a problem the way that this gets
sustained, although it's very understandable why this was important. Important at the
time.
You know, but this isn't, this is saying more of like a
point as opposed to a הלכתי halachic point, right?
This is more of like an attitude.
Right, no, I mean this is actually brought down to הלכה halacha
that you
can't call it, you know, no, I don't know if it's quoted
להלכה, l'halacha, but it's certainly dominant in traditional sources that this is
how they would refer to other religions, you know.
Anyway, all right, so now it says like this, but that's, yeah,
oh, so the other point I wanted to make about this was,
it's actually ironic, too. It's sort of like, if you really want
to תאבדו את שמם, te'avdu et shemam, it's like we just got
through, you know, Purim or whatever, תמחה את
זכר עמלק לא
תשכח.
timcheh et zecher Amalek lo
tishkach.
So, well, not only we say it every year, you have to
remember not to wipe it out. So the process of constantly remembering
it and wiping it out prevents it from being totally wiped out.
If you really wanted it to be wiped out, it wouldn't have
been written in the Torah and we would have forgotten about it
by now. You know, so, ואיבדתם את שמם מן המקום ההוא, ve'ibadetem
et shemam min hamakom hahu, if you really wanted to forget about
it, like who remembers that, you know, you know,
like some places that have totally different names than they used to?
Like what was that song we grew up
with in, exactly, Istanbul was Constantinople, which is why they call it
Byzantium or something? Like if you call it Byzantium, like, huh, who
knew that it was once called Istanbul or once called Constantinople? It's
a totally different name, right? What was those places in Russia that
they renamed, Saint Petersburg and what was it,
Leningrad, Stalingrad? So who, you know, vaguely, I mean, because we have
some history things, but not in people's consciousness, you know, after a
while you don't remember those old names. But instead, so instead, but
it's instead you call it, I don't know, Saint Poopooberg or something
like that. Okay, that would be גנאי, gnai, but then you would
constantly be remembering that it was Saint Petersburg. So, you know, it
is a little bit ironic, right, that the doing of this actually
to some degree sustains the memory. So it's in a way almost
like sustaining that sense of repulsiveness is more important, right, than really
just forgetting about it all together. But, you know, that could be
questioned, you know, like they say, the best way to deal with
a missionary is to ignore them, not to fight them, you know,
if you just, if they just get lost, if it just doesn't
register, then you move on.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying it's going to come back in
every generation, so you need in a sense to keep the...
Yeah, I mean, that's part of it, like the point is that
you want to sustain the awareness in order, because you see this
as an ongoing danger, right, you know.
Okay, so I have a question about what we were talking about
before. So I mean, I guess maybe it's because you really just
can't make something that's, you know, the world אסור assur to anyone,
I guess, if it's not, you just consider you've done nothing, although
you would be killed for it. I just find it hard to
think that like you can still get benefit out of something that
you know you've worshiped, that there's no קנס knas on that to
you.
Yeah, that's, I don't know what to tell you, that's the הלכה.
halacha. Okay, anyway, here I think we're primarily assuming that non-Jews worship
it but not Jews, but we'll get to that a little bit.
Anyway, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Okay, where are we?
Okay, תני תנא קמיה דרב ששת. tani tana kamei d'Rav Sheshet.
העכו"ם, Ha'akum, here for some reason it's העכו"ם Ha'akum even though the
beginning of the פרק perek was הנכרים, Hanochrim, העובדים את ההרים ואת
הגבעות ha'ovdim et heharim ve'et hagevaot that worship the mountains and the
hills, הן מותרים, hen mutarin, the mountains and hills are permissible, ועובדיהם
בסייף, ve'ovdeihem besayif, but the worshipers will get killed by the sword
if it's, you know, if we're imposing the laws of בני נח,
bnei Noach, who are forbidden to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ואת
הזרעים ואת הירקות, ve'et hazra'im ve'et hayrakot, if they worship the seeds
and the vegetables, like the seeds presumably like the wheat, the grains,
and the vegetables that's
growing, הן אסורים ועובדיהם בסייף. hen asurin ve'ovdeihem besayif. They are forbidden
because that's a case of like תפיסת יד אדם, tfisat yad adam,
that sort of like the position of רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili. Presumably you planted the wheat, you planted the vegetable, so it's
forbidden, and the worshipers get the sword. אמר ליה, Amar lei, דאמר
לך מני, d'amar lach mani, so exactly that, so רב ששת Rav
Sheshet said back to the תנא, tana, who told you this, whose
ברייתא braita is this? רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היא, Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi
Yehuda hi, it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר
אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו, d'amar ilan sheneta'o u'levasof avado, if it was
planted and later worshipped, אסור, assur, that it makes it forbidden, at
least the stuff that grows afterwards. So the גמרא Gemara says ולוקמה
באילן שנטעו מתחילה לכך. velokmah be'ilan sheneta'o mitechila lekach. How do you
know, maybe this is a case, even the רבנן Rabanan agree there's
such a thing as an אשרה ashera if it was planted for
that purpose? So maybe the case of the seeds and of the
vegetables are vegetables that were planted for the purpose of being worshipped,
which is pretty funny, a to think that you would do that,
but b also like a vegetable grows, you don't plant a vegetable
once it already exists, you know what I mean? Anyway, so, באילן
שנטעו מתחילה לכך ורבנן, be'ilan sheneta'o mitechila לכך ורבנן,
and it's the רבנן. Rabanan. לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka datchach, דתני
דומיא דהר, detani dumya dehar, like a mountain. מה הר שלא נטעו
מתחילה לכך, Ma har shelo neta'o mitechila lekach, the same way a
mountain wasn't planted for that purpose to be worshipped, a mountain wasn't
planted at all, אף האי נמי שלא נטעו מתחילה לכך. af hai
nami shelo neta'o mitechila lekach. This also, although it was planted, we
want to make it as similar to a mountain as possible. So
we want to assume that it was already growing and part of
the landscape and then you worshipped it. And if even so it
becomes forbidden, that's the position of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Yehuda. איתמר, Itmar, was taught, אבני הר שנידלדלו. avnei har shenidaldalu.
So let's say you have a rock that rolled off of a
mountain. Okay, so what you have here is something that was never
touched by human hands, not humanly constructed, it doesn't have תפיסת יד
אדם tfisat yad adam in that way. On the other hand, it's
not attached to the ground. And what we're going to basically say
is there are two categories of things that we know don't become
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So when you worship them, one is מחובר,
Mechubar, something that's part of the landscape, something that's connected to the
ground. And the other is a בעל חי, Baal Chai, an animal,
okay? If somebody worships an animal, it can't be brought as a
קרבן, Korban, but it's permissible for lay use. It doesn't really become
an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. What about something, so an animal is,
you know, it's not attached to the ground, it's just a natural
part of the world, it's not תפיסת יד אדם, Tfisas Yad Adam,
it's not a human artifact as it were. So what about a
rock? A rock, you know, a boulder or something like that. On
the one hand, it's not attached to the ground. On the other
hand, so maybe it's like an animal, you know, it's not constructed
by a human. If you worship a boulder, what is the story?
So let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, was taught, אבני הר שנדלדלו,
Avnei Har She-Nidaldlu, a rock of a mountain that fell, you know,
rolled, fell off. בני רבי חייא ורבי יוחנן, Bnei Rabbi Chiya Ve-Rabbi
Yochanan, it's a debate between the sons of Rabbi Chiya and Rabbi
Yochanan. חד אמר אסורות, Chad Amar Asurot, they're forbidden if they were
worshipped, וחד אמר מותרות, Ve-Chad Amar Mutarot, they remain permissible. מאי טעמא
דמאן דאמר מותרות, Mai Taama De-Man De-Amar Mutarot, why are they permissible?
כהר, Ke-Har, because it's similar to the mountain case. מה הר שאין
בו תפיסת יד אדם, Mah Har She-Ein Bo Tfisas Yad Adam, the
key is whether it's a human artifact where humans somehow constructed it.
So the same way a mountain was not, you know, handled, controlled
by a human, ומותר, U-Mutar, it's permissible, אף הני נמי שאין בהן
תפיסת יד אדם ומותר, Af Hani Nami She-Ein Bahen Tfisas Yad Adam
U-Mutar, here too, same thing, you know, it's just natural and part
of the natural world. One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, מה להר
שכן מחובר? Mah Le-Har She-Ken Mechubar? That's connected to the ground, something
that's literally part of Mother Earth, that's one thing. Something like a
rock where you could, you know, that becomes raw materials, those are
the types of things that we do take into our, you know,
factories, you move a big boulder, you
may not be able to really
move it, right, okay, but let's assume you can move it. Those
other things we take into our quarries and into our whatever, you
know, they are getting closer to being under human control, you know,
they are, so those maybe are things you can define. So
one minute, so no, מה להר שכן מחובר, Mah Le-Har She-Ken Mechubar,
בהמה תוכיח. Beheimah Tochiach. Ah, wait, we have another category of things
we know don't become עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, at least for lay
use, and that's if you worship a live animal. So מה לבהמה,
Mah Le-Beheimah, so the גמרא Gemara says one, okay, but that's not
just because it's natural. מה לבהמה שכן בעל חי, Mah Le-Beheimah She-Ken
Baal Chai, it's alive. And I really like this גמרא, Gemara, you
know, because it sort of speaks about our control or attempted control
over the, you know, over the like physical world, right? It's like
something that has its own life until you kill it, until it
becomes inanimate, remains somewhat independent of us. You know, we like, you
know, we take physical like, you know, we take physical stuff and
we shape it into other stuff, you know, but things that are
still attached to the ground are not yet raw materials. I mean,
they are, they can be the source of raw materials, right, but
they're still part of the ground, they're not under our control. And
live things, even if they're in our, in our, in our barns
or whatever, are still independent, you know, entities, right? They have their
own life.
So these types of things are more separate from us than just
some raw material that's not attached to the
ground. Okay, so where were we? מה לבהמה שכן בעל חי, Mah
Le-Beheimah She-Ken Baal Chai, הר יוכיח. Har Yochiach. Okay, but let's go
back to the mountain, and this is the גמרא's Gemara case which
is we can give separate reasons for each of them, מחובר Mechubar
and בעל חי, Baal Chai, but if we want to look at
them at the same time, we have to try to find a
common denominator. And being part of the ground or being alive is
not the common denominator. The only common denominator is they have yet
to be somehow shaped by human hands, okay? וחזר הדין, V-Chazar Ha-Din,
so מה לבהמה שכן בעל חי, Mah Le-Beheimah She-Ken Baal Chai, הר
יוכיח, Har Yochiach, and וחזר הדין, V-Chazar Ha-Din, it goes back and
forth. לא ראי זה כראי זה, Lo Rei Zeh Ke-Rei Zeh, ולא
ראי זה כראי זה. Ve-Lo Rei Zeh Ke-Rei Zeh. The unique characteristics
of one are not like the unique characteristics of the other and
vice versa. הצד השוה שבהן, Ha-Tzad Ha-Shaveh She-Bahen, the common side, the
common denominator, שאין בהן תפיסת יד אדם. She-Ein Bahen Tfisas Yad Adam.
The only thing common between those two is that they're not controlled
by human hands. Okay, doesn't mean like not controlled, like, you know,
you ride your horse or whatever, but anyway, not shaped, it's not
a human artifact. אף כל שאין בה תפיסת יד אדם ומותר. Af
Kol She-Ein Bah Tfisas Yad Adam U-Mutar. Similarly, anything that's not, you
know, shaped by human hands ומותר U-Mutar is permissible. So that's why
I say that even a rock is, if you worship it, it's
not a problem. Okay, now I again want to be clear because,
you know, there still is if I go ahead and I take
the rocks and I make them into a little statue or of
מרקוליס Markolis and I bow down to it, it is forbidden. So
it's more, it's not just like physically transformed by human hands, right,
but it's still somehow that it's just there, the rock is just
sitting there. You know, we'll get to a case where I move
the rocks and I build it into something, that's a different story.
But something that on the one hand is not attached to the
ground, is not alive, but on the other hand has never been
touched by human hands.
Yeah, the rock is the altar.
Right, a rock is an altar, you put them all together, right,
but anyway, but you know, but something that's like just there, okay,
does that become defined? So that, so the first position is no,
you don't make that an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah just like you
don't make the other things an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. You get
חייב מיתה, Chayav Misah, but it's not an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Okay, ומותר. U-Mutar. One minute, so the גמרא Gemara says ומותר. U-Mutar.
One minute, מה
הצד השוה שבהן שכן לא נשתנו מברייתן? Mah Ha-Tzad Ha-Shaveh She-Bahen She-Ken
Lo Nishtanu Mi-Beriyatan? One minute, no. So, because this rock, you
know, if the rock actually, we're not just סתם stam talking about
a rock that's in the middle of a forest somewhere. We're talking
about a boulder that came off of a mountain. So that underwent
some transformation. It's not in its fully natural state. So at least
a mountain and an animal are in their fully natural state. A
rock that got dislodged from a mountain has undergone some transformation. אלא,
Ella, so the גמרא Gemara says, come on, like everything undergoes transformation.
I don't understand why we don't call like this animal was, you
know, used to be a calf, and now it's a, you know,
now it's a big animal or something. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara
has a different answer. אתיא מבהמה בעלת מום מהא. Asya mibehema ba'alas
mum me'ha. I'll give you an animal that has undergone transformation. Let's
say it got a wound, let's say, I don't know, it broke
its leg, you know, something like that, that significantly changed it. You
could still worship it and make, if you worshipped it and you
would not make it עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It doesn't matter whether
it's transformed, it matters that it's like totally natural. Okay. ואי נמי
מבהמה תמה ומאילן יבש. Vinami mibehema tama umi'ilan yavesh. Or
I'll give you another example, let's give an example not that the
animal underwent transformation, but that the earth underwent, you know, a part
of the earth underwent transformation. A tree was alive and beautiful, and
then it got dried out and withered and somebody worshipped it. It
wouldn't make it עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, even though it's not in
its original natural form, you know, I mean, you know, it's so
insane too about a rock that rolled off. As long as it
has not been changed by human hands or controlled by human hands,
you should not be able to make it עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
It's part of the natural world. It doesn't matter that it changed.
Okay.
ומאן דאסר, Umande assar, okay, and how about, so that explains the
one that says it's permissible. It's not, it's like a בהמה, behema,
it's like an animal and a mountain. How about the one that
says it's forbidden?
Lahu would say,
להכי כתיב שקץ תשקצנו ותעב תתעבנו. lahachi kasiv shaketz teshaktzenu vesa'ev tesa'avenu.
That's what we learned from this general attitude of despise it, you
know, it should be repulsive. דאף על גב, De'af al gav, that
attitude is telling you something about the halakhic process. This is really
fascinating. Remember how before that idea of שקץ תשקצנו shaketz teshaktzenu shaped
the idea of אבדתם את שמם, ibadtem es shemam, that it's not
enough just to erase the name, you have to make it repulsive.
So here too, this tells us, this attitude of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah being disgusting and distant means, try to make, don't make, don't,
when you're doing your hermeneutics and trying to determine the scope of
a problem, you should not try to narrow the scope of the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah problem, you should try to expand it because
it's so disgusting. Okay. דאף על גב דאתיא מדינא, De'af al gav
de'asya midina, even though you could use a logical derivation to say
that this, you know, boulder is permissible because of the common shared
side with a mountain and an animal, לא תעשייה, lo sa'asya, don't
make this derivation, limit the scope of the things that are permissible.
What's permissible is something attached to the ground and an animal, but
this boulder is forbidden. Which is really fascinating, like there was a,
the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer Rav Eliezer Waldenberg deals with the question
about going into
a mosque. So when Rav Ovadia Yosef deals with it, he says,
come on, Islam isn't עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you mean, and we
used to דאוון daven in mosques in Iraq, you know, I mean,
I hope, I assume not when they were דאוון davening in them,
but anyway. You know, but the, but Rav Eliezer Waldenberg says, שקץ
תשקצנו ותעב תתעבנו כי חרם הוא, shaketz teshaktzenu vesa'ev tesa'avenu ki cherem
hu, blah blah blah, and therefore it's עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Like
you know, like what, like it's not עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But
it's almost similar to this גמרא. Gemara. Now this גמרא Gemara is
different. Here somebody did a real act of worshipping עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, and we have to decide is the rock forbidden or is
the rock permissible. You know, that's a little different than using this
attitude to include things in the category of עבודה זרה avodah zarah
that are not עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But it is fascinating that
the גמרא Gemara is bringing up this attitude as a part of
like a herm- and part of the sort of halakhic process, you
know, not just about an, like an emotional, you know, or a
visceral attitude. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, in the Bronx there's actually a
שבת Shabbat מנין minyan that meets in
a mosque over in Parkchester today, actually tomorrow. Got it, got it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Now, תסתיים
דבני רבי חייא דשרו. tistayem dibne Rabbi Chiyya d'sharu. Let's assume, so
since it's a debate of the sons of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, let's try to figure out if we
can figure out who says who. Let's try to conclude that it's
the sons of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya that are on the position
that this boulder is permissible. Why would you say that? דבעי חזקיה,
Debayei Chizkiyah, because חזקיה Chizkiyah asked. זקף ביצה להשתחוות לה מהו. Zakaf
beitza le-hishtachavos lah mahu. You took an egg, you went to your
chicken coop, you took an egg, here, here's my
egg, for these four-shelf candy, I took my egg out of the
chicken coop and I put it up there on top of my,
on top of my, you know, my, my wall and I'm, in
order to bow down to it. What's the story?
Reminds me of the Jesus story says זקף לבינה להשתחוות לה. zakaf
leveina le-hishtachavos lah. Oh yeah, that's true.
Okay. So קסלקא דעתך להשתחוות לה והשתחוה לה. kasalka daitach le-hishtachavos lah
ve-hishtachava lah.
Now we thought that the question that was being asked was, right,
now by the way, oh, the one thing you have to know
is חזקיה Chizkiyah is one of the sons of רבי חייא. Rabbi
Chiyya. רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiyya two sons are יהודה Yehuda and חזקיה.
Chizkiyah. So דבעי חזקיה Debayei Chizkiyah is the sons of רבי חייא.
Rabbi Chiyya. So we're going to say from that question it's clear
that חזקיה, Chizkiyah, the son of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, held that
this... how this idea of the rock was permissible. Why? Because we’re
assuming that when he describes the case of the egg, he means
that you actually did bow down to it. וקמיבעיא ליה Vekamiba'aya lei
and here’s the question: האי זקיפותא אי הוי מעשה אי לא הוי
מעשה Hai zekifutsa i havei ma'aseh i lo havei ma'aseh
whether the act of just putting an egg on a wall is
considered enough of an act to transform it or not, to make
it something of תפיסת יד אדם.
tfisas yad adam. Like what, scrambled?
No, as opposed to not doing anything to it. אבל לא זקפה
לא מיתסר, Aval lo zakfah lo mitsar, if you just bowed down
to the egg in the chicken coop, it wouldn't be a problem.
Right? The fact that he discusses putting it on the wall means:
is this enough of a תפיסת יד אדם tfisas yad adam to
make it a problem? Which shows that something that has not been
touched by human hands, like an egg that was just laid, that
is not attached to the ground and that's also not an animal,
is not a problem. So that's just like the boulder. The egg
is like the boulder if you haven't touched it and he assumes
it’s not a problem and the only question is when you actually
put it on a wall, is that like you have now controlled
it? Is that תפיסת יד אדם? tfisas yad adam? Let's just find
the answer. Okay, so שמע מינה בני רבי חייא דשרו? Shma mina
bnei Reb Chiyah deshru? Does this not tell us that it's the
sons of רבי חייא Reb Chiyah that say things in their natural
forms are permissible if they were never touched, even if not attached
and not a live animal? לא, Lo, no, that's not necessarily the
right way to read it. לא לעולם אימא לך בני רבי חייא
דאסירי. Lo le'olam eima lach bnei Reb Chiyah de'asiri. בני רבי חייא
Bnei Reb Chiyah could be the ones that say natural things that
are not attached and not alive are forbidden. Okay, ואישתחוה לה, Ve'ishtachavah
lah, if you bow down to it, אף על גב דלא זקפה
אסורה. af al gav delo zakfah asura. If you bow down to
an egg in the chicken coop, even if you never touched it,
maybe they would say it's forbidden, like a boulder. Maybe they would
be in the camp that says it's forbidden. והכא במאי עסקינן, Vehacha
bemai askinan, so what's the case here that's debated? So כגון שזקף
ביצה להשתחוות לה ולא השתחוה לה. Kegon shezakaf beitsa lehishtachavosei lah velo
ishtachavah lah.
You put it up on the wall for the purpose of bowing
down to it. That's the, you know, that was the scenario, but
it never says you bow down to it. So if you bowed
down to the egg in the chicken coop, forbidden. That's not, so
maybe they're that camp. So what's the question? Here a completely different
question. You never bowed down to it, you just put it on
the wall. So now the Gemara says, wait a minute, what type
of question is that? Okay,
ולמאן, Uleman, according to which opinion are you asking this? אי למאן
דאמר עבודת כוכבים של ישראל אסורה מיד. Ei leman de'amar avodas kochavim
shel Yisrael asura miyad. So there's a debate about if a Jew
makes an idol for the purpose of worshipping it, when does it
become forbidden? As soon as the idol comes out of the, you
know, factory, as soon as the idol is made, as soon as
he hits it the last bang? Or only when he worships it?
So the Gemara says, so what's this question about the egg? It
should directly track to that other debate, assuming it's a Jew that
did the egg on the, put the egg on the wall. If
you say an idol of a Jew is forbidden immediately, של ישראל
אסורה, shel Yisrael asura, so even if it wasn't worshipped, then אסורה,
asura, then it's forbidden. אי למאן דאמר עד שתעבד, Ei leman de'amar
ad shete'aved,
according to the one that says an idol of a Jew is
only forbidden once it's worshipped, so then הא לא פלחה, ha lo
palchei, you didn't worship it. So why is this egg a special
case? If the case is you didn't worship it, it should immediately
fall into this debate. So it says, no, לא, lo, צריכא, tzricha,
you need it for the following scenario: כגון שזקף ביצה להשתחוות לה
ולא השתחוה לה. kegon shezakaf beitsa lehishtachavosei lah velo ishtachavah lah.
You put it up on the wall to bow down, you didn't
bow down to it, so and we're assuming that an idol made
by a Jew is only forbidden once it's worshipped. So you haven't
worshipped it yet. Okay, still okay. ובא עובד כוכבים והשתחוה לה. Uva
oved kochavim vehishtachavah lah.
Your next door neighbor, the non-Jew said, 'Oh look, I see you're
getting ready to create, to bow down to this egg god or
whatever it is, let me come and do it before him.' And
I'll come ahead and he did it. Okay, and now a non-Jew
cannot normally bow down to my object and make it forbidden. But
maybe because I set it up to be something to be worshipped,
I've signaled that I would be, I'm okay if people worship it.
And therefore he can define its status by worshipping it because it's
not against my will. Okay, כי הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Ki ha de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, like the case of רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. ישראל שזקף לבנה,
Yisrael shezakaf liveinah, that's the case Michael was talking about. A Jew
that puts a brick up on the wall, okay, and rather than
lying it, you know, down and flat, he lies it straight up
so it's very visible that it's a separate thing, that it's being
erected for a purpose. להשתחוות לה. Lehishtachavosei lah. ובא עובד כוכבים והשתחוה
לה אסורה. Uva oved kochavim vehishtachavah lah asura. And the non-Jew bows
down to it, it's forbidden. Okay, so then why should, what makes
the egg case special?
Well, because a לבנה liveinah is man-made to begin with and an
egg isn't.
Right, okay, but here it's less about the man-made because remember we
would assume even if you bowed down to it in the coop
it would be an issue. Here it's the question about what do
you signal by putting an egg on a wall is very different
than what you might signal by putting, by putting a brick up
on this way. You know, this makes it look like that's a
weird thing, why are you erecting putting that brick like this? See
the bricks are being laid like this. So that's a clear signal
that this is something to be worshipped. But if you put an
egg on a wall, who knows what the heck you're doing? Right?
Okay, okay, וקמיבעיא ליה לבנה הוא דמינכרא זקיפותה. vekamiba'aya lei liveinah hu
deminchara zekifutsei. Maybe that's only by a brick where it's very obvious
it's being erected and therefore anybody who comes who bows down to
it is doing it, you know, according to your, it's you're okay
with that and therefore it could forbid it. אבל ביצה לא. Aval
beitsa lo. Do we say an egg, you know, it's just an
egg on a wall. It's not like it's being erected. או דלמא
לא שנא. O dilma lo shana. Or maybe not. Since that was
your intent, even though it's not visibly obvious to other people, so
maybe nevertheless it was your intent and therefore somebody
who
worshipping something that is part of the natural world, that has never
been touched by human hands, and at the same time is not
attached to the ground and is not an animal.
Okay, and we don't know actually, we didn't decide
either way who we פוסקים pasken like. Correct. Now, בעי רמי בר
חמא: Ba'i Rami Bar Chama: משתחוה להר רבנן מהו למזבח? Mishtachaveh lehahar
ravnan mahu l'mizbe'ach? Now, I remember I told you that if you
worship an animal, the animal can be eaten by humans, or by,
you know, it could be, you can get הנאה hana'ah from it
in terms of your own use, if somebody worshipped an animal, but
it can't be brought as a sacrifice. We learned that from a
special פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so now the question is in parallel, we
now have these two things that if worshipped do not become forbidden:
animals and things that are part of the ground. Okay, so we
want to know, it's a very reasonable question, animals we know if
worshipped can't be used as sacrifices. Let's say you, somebody worshipped a
mountain, can you now quarry stones from that mountain and use it
to build in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? Would it have a
parallel status like an animal? And it's really a double question. On
the one hand, right, animals even though they're alive are still more
under human control than a just סתם stam mountain. You know, I
have my animals in my pen and in my whatever, in my
barn and so on.
Certainly any animal you could use as a קרבן.
korban. Right, so therefore you can more understand that an animal could
be defined at least to be forbidden to the altar more than
a mountain. Number two, it's much worse using something directly for a
sacrifice, to offer it to God, than it is maybe to use
it just as some raw material, you know, to build in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, at least that would seem that way.
Let's say even a מזבח.
mizbe'ach. To build an altar, right. So maybe the walls, maybe not
the altar.
Anyway, I can see the irony, but you know, on the other
hand, I mean wouldn't you say that, you know, how would you
ever do anything? You don't know what a mountain's been through.
Right, which is exactly part of that whole point, exactly, like how
are you going to make the ground, you know, the landscape
forbidden? So, יש נעבד במחובר אצל גבוה או אין נעבד במחובר אצל
גבוה? yesh ne'evad bimchubar eitzel gavo'ah o ein ne'evad bimchubar eitzel gavo'ah?
And it's a two-part question, says the גמרא. Gemara. When you worship
something attached to the ground, does that have an effect in terms
of its status vis-a-vis, you know, God? You know, if it doesn't
affect in terms of humans does it affect from, you know, does
it still have some עבודה זרה avodah zarah status, forbidden status vis-a-vis
the use for divine, you know, for holy purposes? So wait, what's
יש נעבד yesh ne'evad again? Is, does it have a status of
being an נעבד, ne'evad, of a worshipped object, you know, something that
is attached to the ground, does it get a status of a
worshipped object as far as temple use is concerned? Right? The same
way we know that a בהמה beheimah does, but maybe, maybe something
מחובר mechubar is less in our control than a בהמה beheimah and
doesn't get that status even for temple
concern. ואם תמצא לומר יש נעבד במחובר אצל גבוה, Ve'im timtzo lomar
yesh ne'evad bimchubar eitzel gavo'ah, and if it does have that status,
okay, then still you still have to say another
point. מכשירי קרבן כקרבן דמו לא? Machshirei korban kekorban damyu lo? Is
something that there that enables a sacrifice to be brought, like an
altar, like a sacrifice? To say you can't offer it to God
as a sacrifice is like probably that would be the most offensive,
but a מזבח mizbe'ach is one degree removed. So would that be
a problem or not? So, אמר רבא, amar Rava, so Rava says,
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, I'll say that it's forbidden from a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, based on an אתנן. esnan. Because an אתנן esnan
is a gift to a, to a prostitute, or payment of a
prostitute I should say. And we're going to learn that that payment
is forbidden even to not only as a sacrifice but even to
be used for any temple purpose. Okay, and therefore we're going to
make a קל וחומר: kal vachomer: if a payment to a prostitute
is forbidden, certainly a worshipped object is forbidden. Now, okay, but let's
take a look. אמר רבא קל וחומר ומא אתנן, Amar Rava kal
vachomer uma esnan, the payment to a
prostitute, שמותר בתלוש להדיוט, shemutar betalush l'hedyo, that if you actually, if
it were something that wasn't attached to the ground, right, and there
was money that was given to a prostitute, or I don't know
some some object, other, you know, people could get benefit from it,
it doesn't become there's never a case a payment to a prostitute
is forbidden for normal people to get use out of it. Okay,
it's not like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, and nevertheless אסור במחובר
לגבוה. asur bimchubar l'gavo'ah. If somebody gave a house to a prostitute
and then she wanted to or a tree, an attached tree to
a prostitute, and then she wanted to chop it down and use
it in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it wouldn't be allowed. Okay,
so on the one hand, you've got the, you know, it never
is forbidden for lay use, and on the other hand, exactly parallel
to our case, something that's attached to the ground given to a
prostitute can't be used not only for a sacrifice but for any
temple purpose. Okay, so that's exactly like our case. So, and that's
a case where something where it's never forbidden to a normal person.
So, now how do you know this is true about a prostitute?
Well, wait a minute. אתנן שמותר להדיוט אסור במחובר לגבוה דכתיב, Esnan
shemutar l'hedyo asur bimchubar l'gavo'ah dichsiv, you know it because it says,
לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב, lo tavi esnan zonah umchir kelev,
don't bring the payment to a prostitute or the exchange of a
dog, בית ה׳ אלקיך Beis Hashem Elokecha to the house of Hashem
your God. לא שנא תלוש ולא שנא במחובר. Lo shena talush velo
shena bimchubar. It doesn't matter whether what you've given her is something
attached or detached. Now, it could just be because the verse doesn't
distinguish. רש״י Rashi also says it's the end of the verse: לא
תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב בית. lo tavi esnan zonah umchir kelev
bayis. Even if what you gave her was a house, you can't
use that house. And we also read the verse בית ה׳ אלקיך.
Beis Hashem Elokecha. Don't only not bring it as a קרבן. korban.
Don't use it for any temple purpose. Okay, so for the, for
the prostitute, we understand,
even
if it's מחובר, m'chubar, you can't use it for any temple purpose.
And that's a something which is never forbidden to a lay person.
Okay, so
נפקא, nafka, so cases
of something worshipped שאסור בתלוש להדיוט, she'assur b'talush l'hedyot, if it were
something that was detached, an idol, that was worshipped, it's forbidden to
all lay people. Okay, so obviously something worshipped is a heavier status.
So in that case
אצל הדיוט מותר במחובר לגבוה, etzel hedyot mutar b'm'chubar l'gavoah, שנאמר אלוהיהם
על ההרים ולא ההרים אלוהיהם. she'ne'emar elokeihem al he'harim v'lo he'harim elokeihem.
לא שנא להדיוט ולא שנא לגבוה. Lo sh'na l'hedyot v'lo sh'na l'gavoah.
I skipped a line, right? Yeah, I
skipped a line. ולא שנא במחובר נפקא, v'lo sh'na b'm'chubar nafka, שאסור
בתלוש להדיוט, she'assur b'talush l'hedyot, אינו דין שאסור במחובר לגבוה? eino din
she'assur b'm'chubar l'gavoah? How much more so should this be forbidden. Okay,
so if an אתנן זונה esnan zonah in an exactly parallel case
is forbidden to use in the temple, then something that is worshipped
is certainly forbidden to use in the temple, because something that is
worshipped clearly is weightier than a gift to a prostitute. Okay, that's
a good point. So let's see the end. Of course, there could
be distinctions, but okay. The distinction could be when I give something
to a prostitute, if I give her a house, she owns it.
It still has the status of payment to a prostitute. Whereas if
I worship a mountain, it could be it never has a status
of something being worshipped. It's like it's a meaningless act, you know
what I mean? Like it's I didn't have control over it the
same way I had control over the house that I gifted, anyway
that I paid. Anyway, but that's the argument. If it's forbidden in
the case of the prostitute, it should certainly be forbidden in the
case of being
worshipped. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא. Amar lei Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rava. So Rav Huna the son of Rav
Yehoshua said to Rava: וחילוף, v'chiluf, maybe I should make the, I
agree totally with your קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but he says, but
how do you know to start with what you assume is the
fact by the prostitute and then apply it to the case of
the thing that was worshipped? You know that a prostitute is forbidden,
and you're going to therefore say the thing that's worshipped is forbidden.
Let's go the opposite direction. Let's start with the assumption that the
thing that worshipped is permissible, and then learn that the gift to
the prostitute is
permissible. וחילוף, v'chiluf, let me go in the opposite
direction. ומה נעבד שאסור בתלוש אצל הדיוט מותר במחובר לגבוה. u'mah ne'evad
she'assur b'talush etzel hedyot mutar b'm'chubar l'gavoah. Let's start this way. Something
worshipped, if it was something that was detached, normal people can't get
benefit from it, and nevertheless, if it's part of the landscape, you
can use it even in the temple. Let's start with that assumption.
Why should I say you could use it even in the
temple? שנאמר אלוהיהם על ההרים ולא ההרים אלוהיהם. she'ne'emar elokeihem al he'harim
v'lo he'harim elokeihem. Like I was saying before, like it's just fundamentally
the mountain never gets defined as a god. It's like nothing ever
happened. You know, nothing happened here. Move along. Okay, so it's like
so let's start with the assumption that it's a meaningless act to
worship a mountain, to say that that defines the mountain, and you
could use it even in the temple. And once that's true, I'll
say: Oh, if you could use that in the temple, you could
certainly use a gift to a prostitute that was attached to the
ground in a
temple. לא שנא להדיוט ולא שנא לגבוה. Lo sh'na l'hedyot v'lo sh'na
l'gavoah. So it's just בכלל b'chlal not thing like something that was
ever worshipped. If that's true there, אתנן שמותר בתלוש להדיוט, esnan she'mutar
b'talush l'hedyot, so an אתנן esnan that a normal lay person can
derive benefit
from, אינו דין שמותר במחובר לגבוה? eino din she'mutar b'm'chubar l'gavoah? How
much more so if somebody gives a house to a prostitute, should
she be able, should you be able to use it in the
temple. So we all agree that the case of worshipped is much
weightier. But the question is which הלכה halacha do we start by
assuming? Do we start by assuming that the case of the prostitute
can't be used if it was attached and therefore the something worshipped
certainly can't be used, or do we start the opposite? Something worshipped
that was attached can be used and therefore certainly the gift to
the prostitute can be used. So he says, how do you know
what way to go? Okay. ואי משום בית ה' אלוהיך, V'ee mishum
Beis Hashem Elokecha, now you'll tell me one minute, it says the
house of Hashem your God and you want to say that means
that even something attached and even that can't be used in any
temple purpose. That's what you want to learn out from בית ה'.
Beis Hashem. And that's what's making you say that we know the
הלכה halacha by the case of the prostitute that it's forbidden. He
says you don't have to learn it that
way. מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Mibai lei l'chidetanya, you can learn it to
teach you
what the ברייתא braita teaches. בית ה' אלוהיך, Beis Hashem Elokecha, פרט
לפרה שאינה באה לבית, prat l'parah she'eina ba'ah l'bayis, דברי רבי אלעזר.
divrei Rabbi Elazar. This is an amazing idea. The פרה אדומה parah
adumah which is used to cleanse from impurity can come from a
gift to a prostitute. Okay, don't use it for something associated with
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay, but something that was, you know,
never being brought to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, not part of
the structure of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, never brought as a
קרבן, korban, you can use it. So somebody gives a פרה אדומה
parah adumah to a prostitute, and she can go ahead and use
it for, you can use it for פרה אדומה. parah adumah. That's
one thing we learn from בית ה'. Beis Hashem. One minute, וחכמים
אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, now the חכמים Chachamim say no. לרבות את הריקועין.
l'rabos es ha'rikuin. No, no, no, that's actually coming to say that
even things that are like
some type of gold plating that you're going to do, even if
it's, you know, that would be forbidden. Meaning that it is forbidden
not only to use it as a sacrifice, it's forbidden to use
it for temple purposes. Okay, that's what בית ה' Beis Hashem tells
you, but only Only if it was detached; something that was attached
to the ground maybe would not be forbidden, so maybe you're right
that it's not only forbidden as a קרבן, korban, it's even forbidden
to use in some temple purpose like for gold plating. But he
says it's not clear that the case of a gift to the
prostitute, the אתנן, esnan, includes something attached to the ground. So why
do you start by assuming that's forbidden and then say the case
of worship is forbidden? I'll say the opposite, I'll start by the
case of worship, a mountain top is permissible
for the temple and therefore say by the אתנן esnan also something
that was attached to the ground is permissible. So how do you
know which way to start? David had a question before.
David: I don't exactly know
how to verbalize it,
but it seems like they're putting more importance on the sticks and
stones in
terms of the temple than on the intent in terms of this
red cow which is the source of purity for all these people
coming from an impure source.
Right, I know, that's what I was pointing out. I was pointing
out that irony, yeah, exactly. So the beginning part, the extension that
we weren't debating is whether it's מחובר mechubar or whether that can
be forbidden because everyone agrees it was תלוש. talush. Yeah, yeah, it's
all about מחובר. mechubar. It's all about מחובר. mechubar. Okay, so you're
right that a prostitute is not as weighty as worship, but why
do you start by assuming מחובר mechubar by a prostitute is forbidden
and apply it to worship? Let's assume by saying worship מחובר mechubar
is permissible for the temple and apply that to prostitute. Okay, it's
good question. So he
says, אמר ליה אנא קאמינא לחומרא ואת אמרת לקולא. amar lei ana
kamina lechumra ve'at amarta lekula. Says, okay you're right, you could go
either way, but my way leads to being playing it safe, being
strict, saying
don't use the gift of the prostitute, don't use the rocks
for the temple. I'm going to conclude a strict way. You want
to go lenient, you want to say use the rocks for the
temple and use the gift of the house that was given to
the prostitute for the temple. I want to be strict, you want
to be lenient. So קולא וחומרא, kula vechumra, if you're going to
be lenient or
strict, לחומרא פרכינן lechumra parchinan we go the strict way. Now that
doesn't mean now this for עבודה זרה? avoda zara? No, well that's
good point, רש"י Rashi does not seem to think that it means
just for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But it doesn't also mean like
in general, like of course there's some people that that's their attitude
to הלכה, halacha, anytime you can be strict, be strict. No, but
what it means is is that if you have two ways you
can go with a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's more like a
hermeneutic principle. If you have two ways you can go with a
קל וחומר kal vachomer and you don't know which way to learn
it out, so the hermeneutics tells you go the strict way rather
than that's yeah but it's not again it's not כוח דהיתר, koach
de-heiter, it's not a פסק, psak, it's a principle. What how do
we apply a קל וחומר kal vachomer when we don't know which
way to go? And according to at least his claim, the גמרא
Gemara is going to challenge it, but his claim is that we
apply it in the strict version. Now, that's a claim, okay, we'll
see in a minute, but I want to also say something about
the word that רש"י Rashi says פרכינן. parchinan. פרכינן parchinan means we
ask. Why do you say פרכינן? parchinan? This is about making a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, learning something, not challenging something. So רש"י Rashi
says it's because every derivation of a קל וחומר kal vachomer comes
with a rhetoric question, doesn't it? Anyway, which is a קל וחומר
kal vachomer if it's true in this case where it's the light
case, in the weighty case, shouldn't it certainly be true, לא כל
שכן? lo kol sheken? So since a קל וחומר kal vachomer always
ends with a rhetorical question, isn't it certainly true in this case?
The way of saying we make a קל וחומר kal vachomer here,
the word used is פרכינן, parchinan, we ask, meaning we ask sort
of
rhetorically, it certainly should be true in this case. Anyway, so really?
What? Really? Yeah, exactly. So anyway, so anyway, that's his point, that
the hermeneutic principle is you go strict, okay, but the גמרא Gemara
is
going to question that. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא וכל היכא דאיכא
קולא וחומרא לקולא לא פרכינן? amar lei Rav Pappa le-Rava ve-chol heicha
de-ika kula ve-chumra le-kula lo parchinan? Are you telling me we never
go lenient when we make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you always
go
strict? So והא דהזאה דפסח דפליגי רבי אליעזר ורבי עקיבא. ve-ha de-haza'ah
de-Pesach de-pligi Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Akiva. There's a debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva about somebody who's seventh day
they were טמאי מת, tmei mes, they got טמאי מת tmei mes
a week before פסח. Pesach. Their seventh day fell out on ערב
פסח. erev Pesach. So what they should be able to do is
sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה para aduma on me, make
me טהור tahor and I'll bring my קרבן פסח korban Pesach today
and I'll eat it tonight, meaning I won't be fully טהור tahor
till tonight, but I'll eat it tonight, somebody will bring it for
me. However, and then if I don't bring it and I didn't
get my ashes sprinkled on me, then you know I'm חייב chayav
for not bringing it and so on, because I had the option
of bringing it etc. Okay, so question if I got the ashes
sprinkled and didn't bring it or didn't get the ashes sprinkled, anyway
I'll bracket that. So,
but
that would be normal, but it just so happens that today ערב
פסח erev Pesach is also a שבת. Shabbos. And normally you're not
allowed to sprinkle the ashes of a פרה אדומה para aduma on
somebody רבנןically, rabanan practically speaking on שבת. Shabbos. So but in this
case where if we don't sprinkle it, he won't be able to
bring his קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, do we override שבת, Shabbos, the
רבנןic rabanan restriction of שבת Shabbos and go ahead and sprinkle it
anyway? Okay, so this is a debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Why don't we not want to use it on שבת? Shabbos? Change
of status? Yeah exactly, like going to the מקווה, mikvah, although going
to the מקווה mikvah looks like you're just bathing, but this is
clearly changing status. Okay, so this is the debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So to say now it's
interesting, I might say to let me sprinkle is being lenient because...
So letting, you’re overriding your שבת Shabbos restriction, you’re letting me bring
a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, but the גמרא’s Gemara understanding is that
that’s the strict approach because that means that there’s now an expectation
that you have to get it done and that you have to
bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So it actually translates into a
demand on you. Okay, so that’s the strict side of it. Okay,
and to do we sprinkle or not, and that’s a question of
a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. Okay? דפליגי De-pligi רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
ורבי עקיבא. and Rabbi Akiva. דרבי אליעזר De-Rabbi Eliezer סבר לחומרא savar
l’chumra that we’re strict and we allow/demand that he gets sprinkled and
that he brings his קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, וחייב עליה לגבוה v’chayav
aleih l’gavoha and he says if you didn’t get sprinkled and bring
your קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you’ve transgressed. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva לקולא
ופטור l’kula u’patur and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it’s lenient and
he exempts the guy from bringing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Now,
so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wants to make it to argue to
be lenient as it were, to not demand this of him. וקא
פריך V’ka parich רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva לקולא l’kula and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva wants to make a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer for the
sake of being lenient. Even you can make the קל וחומר Kal
Vachomer both ways. How is that? דלא. D’lo. השיב רבי עקיבא. Heshiv
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva responded to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was רבי עקיבא’s Rabbi Akiva רבי. Rebbe. או
חילוף, O chiluf, I’ll say the opposite. And now the קל וחומר
Kal Vachomer was, here was רבי אליעזר’s Rabbi Eliezer קל וחומר. Kal
Vachomer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, I don’t understand, it’s שבת Shabbos
ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. What are you going to do? You’re going
to שחט shacht the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. You’re going to bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. The קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach itself overrides today שבת. Shabbos. So certainly sprinkling should override שבת.
Shabbos. Pretty good argument. Okay.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said the opposite. השיב
רבי עקיבא. Heshiv Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva responded, או חילוף,
O chiluf, I can argue the opposite to you. ומה הזיה שמשום
שבות אינה דוחה את השבת, U’ma ha-za’ah she-mishum shvout eina docha es
ha-Shabbos, I’ll start with the assumption of the opposite. You’re starting with
the one assumption, I’ll start with the other assumption. Sprinkling doesn’t override
שבת. Shabbos. שחיטה שדאורייתא לא כל שכן?
Shechita she-d’Oraisa lo kol
she-ken? And normally, we know that as a normal rule. So certainly
you shouldn’t be able to שחט shacht the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
on שבת. Shabbos. And therefore I want to conclude that say that
it’s אסור assur to sprinkle. Now of course that’s absurd, because everybody
agrees you שחט shacht the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay. So this is a very bizarre that the גמרא Gemara wants
to bring this. Obviously he was making a silly like not a
real argument, which we’ll have to understand in a minute. Okay, but
right now the face of it he’s saying, ah look, you see
he wants to make a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer and go in
the opposite direction, start with the opposite assumption, and come to a
lenient conclusion. So the גמרא Gemara says, so don’t you see that
he’s doing it to be lenient? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
התם רבי אליעזר גמרא גמרי. Hasam Rabbi Eliezer gemara gamrei. One minute,
no no. There, you don’t understand the whole background because it was
a silly argument by רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva anyway. Of course you
שחט shacht the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. The point
is that there was a subtext to the argument because רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, רבי עקיבא’s Rabbi Akiva רבי, Rebbe, had taught רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that you don’t sprinkle on
ערב פסח Erev Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer had gotten old and he forgot his
learning. ויקר ליה תלמודא. V’yakar lei talmuda. ויקר V’yakar means forgot? I
thought יקר yakar is
like, you know, heavy.
Maybe got like heavy for him, like somehow it means it was...
he was, yeah, but right, okay. ואתא רבי עקיבא לאדכוריה. V’asa Rabbi
Akiva l’adkoria. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was trying to make a silly
argument but that the subtext was to remind him that it’s obvious
you don’t sprinkle on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. והיינו דאמר
ליה, V’hainu d’amar lei, and that’s why, you know, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer didn’t pick up on it. Okay. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
said back to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, what type of a silly point is that? Of course you
bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos. And therefore in
the end, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had to be more explicit. He
couldn’t do it by subtlety, so he had to be explicit. והיינו
דאמר ליה, V’hainu d’amar lei, and that’s why the משנה mishna ends
that he says to him: רבי, Rebbe, אל תחפירני בשעת הדין. al
tachpireni b’shat ha-din. Rebbe,
please don’t deny to me something when we’re arguing. Something that you
deep down know is true. כך מקובלני ממך. Kach mekubalani mimcha. This
actually is the tradition I have from you. שזו שבות ואינה דוחה
את השבת, She-zo shvout v’eina docha es ha-Shabbos, that it doesn’t override
שבת. Shabbos. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was making a silly argument
so he didn’t have to say it explicitly. In the end he
was forced to say it explicitly. But at the end of the
day, the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that if you have a
קל וחומר Kal Vachomer and you don’t know which way to go,
you don’t know which הלכה halacha to assume, do you assume the
light one and apply it to the heavy one, or do you
assume the heavy one anyway, which way, the גמרא’s Gemara saying you’re
going to go the strict way. And therefore since we can go
both ways with this קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, okay, we’re going to
go the strict way and say you cannot use the stones of
the mountain for a base... for an altar, and we’ll learn... we’ll
assume that הלכה halacha by the case of the אתנן, esnan, the
gift to the... the payment to the prostitute, and then we’ll apply
it and be strict to the case of
the.
So it's interesting here, 'cause רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva usually is the
one who does exegesis, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is the one
who was into tradition.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
It's ironic. That's a very interesting point.
But
who was the one who was put in the חרם? cherem? רבי
אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, so that's interesting.
So and then he start—he forgot his תלמוד. Talmud.
Oh, maybe that's related. That's a good point, that he was all
about just the memory and not the derivation. Yeah, I have to
think about that, that's a good point. Okay, let's just get to
the bottom. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'i Rami bar Chama. Okay, so
that's about whether you can use the stones in the altar, and
presumably the answer is no. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'i Rami bar
Chama. רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked, המשתחוה לקמת חטין מהו
למנחות? Hamishtachaveh lekamat chitin mahu leminachot?
Okay, now we know if you bow down—now we've decided that you
can't use if you worship the natural world, you can't use it
for the altar. What if you now transformed it in a very
significant way? You didn't just hew the stone out of the mountain.
Okay, you bowed down to this grain. The grain now can't be
used as a קרבן, korban, that we sort of concluded above. Okay,
but now you now took the grain and you milled it and
you ground it and you turned it into flour. Can that be
used? Okay. יש שינוי בנעבד? Yesh shinui bene'evad?
Does transforming its whole status make it like it's a new object?
או אין שינוי בנעבד? O ein shinui bene'evad? Now, רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot both point out clearly this is only vis-a-vis the altar.
If you worshipped grain after it was cut, and it becomes forbidden
for personal use—you know, for normal people's use—it doesn't matter if you
transform it or not, it remains totally forbidden. It's not like, oh,
let me take some חזיר chazir and I'll pulverize it and turn
it into soup and then I'll drink it and it's changed. Like
no, it remains forbidden. But when it was—when it was worshipped as
something attached, and it was only forbidden to the altar, it was
not forbidden for normal use, that's our question. Maybe there the change
of form is enough. Okay, יש שינוי בנעבד yesh shinui bene'evad specifically
for the altar, או אין שינוי בנעבד. o ein shinui bene'evad. אמר
מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן תא שמע. Amar Mar Zutra brei d'Rav
Nachman ta shma. Come and hear. You know what, we're going to—because
it's already 8:30—we will end here. We'll pick up with this tomorrow
to figure it out, because it gets a little complicated. Okay, cliffhanger.
Well, so pick it up
then.